A Guide to the John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers FA108
Rockefeller Archive Center
John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers
1906-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
FA108
92.44 Cubic Feet 265 Boxes
Arrangement note
The papers of John D. Rockefeller 3rd are divided into three series:
Series 1 - Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller Files, (1906-1961)-1969.
Series 2 - Rockefeller Family and Associates Files, 1942-(1962-1977).
Series 3 - Office and Home Files, 1928-(1955-1978).
Series 4 - Audiovisual materials.
Due to overlap in years and subject matter among the series, please consult the descriptions and folder listings for all three series when researching a topic.
Biographical/Historical note
John Davison Rockefeller 3rd was born in New York, New York, on March 21, 1906, the eldest son of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He was the brother of Abby Rockefeller Mauzé and Nelson, Laurance, Winthrop, and David Rockefeller.
Rockefeller, whose childhood family nickname was "Demi," received his preparatory education at the Browning School in New York City and the Loomis Institute, Windsor, Connecticut. He went to Princeton University where he received high honors in economics and graduated in 1929 with the degree of bachelor of science. Rockefeller chose industrial relations as the subject of his senior thesis. While attending college, Rockefeller formed interests that would influence his career in philanthropy.
Rockefeller spent the summer prior to his college graduation as an assistant in the Information Section of the League of Nations office in Geneva, Switzerland, thus beginning a lifelong commitment to international relations. A world tour, undertaken after college graduation, concluded with work for the Institute of Pacific Relations conference in Japan.
In December 1929, Rockefeller, who had been reared to assume the lead role in his generation's philanthropic endeavors, began working in his father's office at 26 Broadway in New York. He immersed himself in the operations of the many institutions associated with the family and became a board member or officer of the Rockefeller Foundation, the General Education Board, the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), Colonial Williamsburg, and the China Medical Board, among others.
The young Rockefeller also developed his own interests. Through his work as a member of the board of directors of the Bureau of Social Hygiene (to which he was appointed in 1928), Rockefeller began a lifelong commitment to the issues of population and birth control. In 1932, he became chairman of the Delinquency Committee of the Boys Bureau of New York City. Six years later the Committee published its recommendations for handling youthful offenders in "Youth in the Toils."
On November 11, 1932, at the Riverside Church in New York City, Rockefeller married Blanchette Ferry Hooker, a daughter of Elon Hooker, the founder of Hooker Electrochemical Company, and Blanche Ferry. John and Blanchette had one son, John D. Rockefeller IV, and three daughters: Sandra, Hope, and Alida. They maintained their principal residences in Manhattan and at Fieldwood Farm in Mt. Pleasant (Westchester County), New York.
In July 1942, Rockefeller joined the Navy. He served with the rank of lieutenant commander in the Office of the Chief of Naval Operations and worked in an interagency task force devoted to planning postwar policy for Japan. Rockefeller was released from active duty in 1945, but his wartime experience led to his appointment as cultural consultant to John Foster Dulles during the Japanese peace treaty negotiations. His broad assignment to consider ways to improve U.S.-Japan relations fostered his deep interest in Japan and in all of Asia. Rockefeller came to love the country, its culture, and its people, so much so that Japan became a second home to Rockefeller and his wife. It was during this time, the late 1940s, that he and his wife began collecting Asian art, albeit on an intermittent and amateur basis.
In the early 1950s, Rockefeller revitalized the moribund Japan Society, and in 1956 he organized the Asia Society. Both organizations were devoted to fostering cultural and educational exchanges between the East and the West. He also founded the Council on Economic and Cultural Affairs (later renamed the Agricultural Development Council) to provide assistance to Asian farmers. Rockefeller became the American with whom prominent Asians sought counsel. He was an advocate of moderation and cooperation in foreign affairs.
With the founding of the Population Council in 1952, Rockefeller hoped to bring the problem of overpopulation to global attention. His travels throughout Asia convinced him that population growth had to be checked if underdeveloped countries were to achieve political stability. In 1970, President Nixon appointed Rockefeller to the chairmanship of the Commission on Population Growth and the American Future.
Closer to home, JDR 3rd took leadership of a committee of civic leaders who were working to create Lincoln Center. He became the key figure in fund-raising efforts as well as in forging consensus among the diverse group of civil officials, social leaders, and artists whose cooperation was necessary for the Center to succeed. Rockefeller was the Center's first president, starting in 1956, and became its chairman in 1961, a post in which he served until 1970 when he was elected honorary chairman.
During the 1960s, JDR 3rd and Blanchette became serious collectors of Asian and American art. Sherman Lee, director of the Cleveland Museum of Art and an expert on Asian art, served as a consultant to the Rockefellers, as did Edgar P. Richardson, an expert in American art. Rockefeller viewed himself as the temporary custodian of his works of art; ultimately, his collections would serve the public. Upon his death, his major collections of Oriental and American art were donated to the Asia Society of New York City and the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, respectively.
In the late 1960s, Rockefeller undertook a major campaign to influence public policy on philanthropy, particularly private philanthropy, which he viewed as a unique social force that was indispensable to the continued success of the United States. Rockefeller became the leading spokesperson on private philanthropy. He lobbied Congress for regulatory and tax laws under which private giving could flourish. In his role as self-appointed caretaker of philanthropy, Rockefeller was responsible for the creation of the Commission on Foundations and Private Philanthropy (usually known as the Peterson Commission) and the Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs (usually known as the Filer Commission).
Rockefeller saw great potential in the civil rights and youth movements of the 1960s. In his book, "The Second American Revolution" (1973), for which he drew on his experiences of the 1960s, Rockefeller described his vision of the United States as a pluralistic democracy that emphasized cooperation between public and private institutions. This book set the stage for Rockefeller's involvement in helping to plan for the U.S. bicentennial celebration of 1976. Rockefeller took an active role through his work on the National Committee for the Bicentennial Era and with the money provided by the JDR 3rd Fund for bicentennial projects.
John D. Rockefeller 3rd was killed in an automobile accident in Mt. Pleasant, New York, on July 10, 1978. Following a memorial service at the Riverside Church in New York City, his cremated remains were buried in the Rockefeller Cemetery.
For lengthier biographical sketches of John D. Rockefeller 3rd, see Series 1 (box 1, folder 10) and Series 2 (box 23, folders 203-205) of this collection.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of John D. Rockefeller 3rd (1906-1978), which comprise Record Group 5 of the Rockefeller Family Archives, document Rockefeller's life and philanthropic activities. They provide information on his education; relationships with family, friends, and business associates; travels; and social concerns, including his lifelong involvement in four major areas: population, Asia, philanthropy, and the arts. The records document his concern for the projects and institutions he initiated and developed.
The bulk of the collection is opened for research. Material has been closed that relates to the life and work of living members of the Rockefeller family or to the net wealth of the family or of a single family member. Also, material has been closed that relates to personnel matters or to searches for corporate philanthropic officers.
Related Archival Materials note
In addition to the papers of family members, the Rockefeller Archive Center has numerous collections related to the life and work of John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
Organizations: Agricultural Development Council, Asia Society, Council on Foundations, JDR 3rd Fund, Population Council, Inc., Products of Asia, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, and Rockefeller Foundation.
Associates and advisors: Joan Dunlop, John E. Harr, Raymond Lamontagne, David Lelewer, Elizabeth McCormack, Porter McKeever, Donald H. McLean, Jr., Datus C. Smith, Jr., and Edgar B. Young.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III RG 05.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of John D. Rockefeller 3rd were transferred to the Archive Center from the Rockefeller family offices in Manhattan. Series 1 (Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller Files) and Series 2 (Rockefeller Family and Associates Files) were maintained within the general files department and the archives, the departments responsible for recordkeeping in the family office. The majority of the material designated as Series 3 (Office and Home Files) was maintained in the personal office and homes of Mr. Rockefeller until his death in 1978.
Until the records were processed in final form, Series 1 was maintained at the Archive Center as a discrete series within the Rockefeller Family Archives, RG 2 (Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, 1897-1961); Series 2 was maintained and described as part of the long alphabetical sequence of files that constitutes the Rockefeller Family Archives, RG 3 (Rockefeller Family & Associates, 1962-1978). The archives department of the family office discontinued RG 3 following the death of Mr. Rockefeller 3rd. The current series titles in the John D. Rockefeller 3rd Papers were carried forward from the previous classifications to emphasize this aspect of the provenance.
The general files department created and maintained a card index for the records transferred to the department. This practice continued until the end of 1996. Indexed material was given a markup--either an arbitrary number or a brief title--that was then entered on the relevant index card. This card index, which can be consulted, contains references to specific documents and is not exhaustive. To facilitate use of the index card file, original folder titles have largely been retained except where doing so would hinder access.
Series 3 is, for the most part, composed of material that was not maintained by general files. It includes material that was kept for then-current use in the office and homes of John D. Rockefeller 3rd by Mr. Rockefeller and his associates. It also includes accretions transferred to the Archive Center in the years following the deaths of Mr. and Mrs. Rockefeller, among them files from the office of Joyce Tait, Mr. Rockefeller's personal secretary, and files used by Peter Johnson, an associate of Mr. Rockefeller, in his preparation of the two-volume biography of John D. Rockefeller 3rd that he coauthored with John Harr.
Other Finding Aids
For other JDR photographs please see Series 1007 of:
FA451 JDR 3rd family photographs, Series 1007
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the John D. Rockefeller 3rd Papers:
PRINTED MATERIALS
2 record cartons of annual reports, pamphlets, brochures, etc. from various JDR 3rd-related organizations and interests 10 editions of "The New York Times" from December 8, 1941 through August 11, 1945 New York City newspapers containing reports of death of JDR Jr. on May 11, 1960
PHOTOGRAPHS
See RAC Photograph Collection Number 1007
ARTIFACTS
Glass bottleHair clippingNecktieTooth
Art; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; John D. Rockefeller House (Pocantico Hills, N.Y.); Population; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; Asia; Travel; Rockefeller, John D.; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; Rockefeller family
- Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller Files, 1906-1969 1906-1961; 1; 34.5 Cubic Feet 98 Boxes
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged into seven subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Personal PapersSubseries 2 - Personal CorrespondenceSubseries 3 - Asian InterestsSubseries 4 - Lincoln CenterSubseries 5 - Population InterestsSubseries 6 - TripsSubseries 7 - Financial Material
  - Personal Papers, 1906-1961; 1
    Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries contains information on John D. Rockefeller 3rd's birth, education, engagement, wedding, club memberships, wartime naval service, art collection, and real estate properties. Surviving childhood and school papers include coloring books, autograph collection, notebooks, yearbooks, and examinations. This subseries also contains the congratulatory notes (folder 12) received by JDR 3rd's parents at the time of his birth (including a telegram from Andrew Carnegie), as well as the condolences Rockefeller received upon the death of his grandfather, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., in 1937 (folder 158) and of his mother, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, in 1948 (folders 149-151). Correspondence with John Foster Dulles and handwritten notes document Rockefeller's refusal of the ambassadorship to Indonesia in 1956 (folder 116). News clippings and magazine articles (folders 21-29) on topics of interest to Rockefeller as well as a scrapbook (box 21) that contains clippings about him can also be found in this subseries. Rockefeller's personal diaries from 1920 to 1961 (folders 36-72) are a valuable source of information. Begun at the age of 13 as a record of people, time, and events, the diaries offer a mixture of the routine interlaced with revealing personal insights. In December 1929, when Rockefeller began working in his father's office at 26 Broadway, the format of the diaries changed from handwritten to typescript. At that point, the diaries became more reflective of his business rather than his personal life.
    Related Archival Materials note
    For diaries from 1962 until Rockefeller's death in 1978, see Series 3, subseries 1.
    - Allowance Account, 1920, 1922-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Apartments - One Beekman Place, 1932-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Apartments - Appraisal Inventory, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Apartments - Transfer of, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Apartments - Beekman Hill Neighbors, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Apartments - Proposed New York City, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Autograph Collection, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Awards, 1947-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Awards, 1947-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Biographical Information, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Birth - Certificate, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Birth - Congratulatory Notes, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Birth - News Clippings, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Birthday Greetings, 1919-1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Boats, 1939, 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Boats - "Rockette", 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Boats - "Snow White", 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Childhood Items, 1906-1915, 1918, 1922, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Christmas Greetings, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Christmas Greetings, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Clippings - Biographical Stories, 1923-1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Clippings - Birth Control, 1939, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Clippings - Crime, 1934, 1937, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Clippings - Industrial Relations, 1934-1945, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Clippings - International Relations, 1927-1947 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Clippings - Marriage, 1934-1962 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Clippings - Miscellaneous, 1936-1939, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Clippings - Parents and Children, 1934-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Clippings - Personality, 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Clubs - General, 1941-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Clubs - Memberships, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Clubs - Cap and Gown Club, 1928-1961 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Clubs - Kittansett Club, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Clubs - Lunch Club, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Clubs - Yeamans Hall Club, 1938-1961 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Diaries, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Diaries, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Diaries, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Diaries, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Diaries, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Diaries, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Diaries, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Diaries, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Diaries, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Diaries, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Diaries, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Diaries, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Diaries, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Diaries, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Diaries, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Diaries, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Diaries, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Diaries, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Diaries, 1941-February 1946 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Diaries, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Diaries, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Diaries, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Diaries, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Diaries, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Diaries, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Diaries, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Diaries, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Diaries, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Diaries, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Diaries, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Diaries, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Diaries, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Diaries, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Diaries, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Diaries, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Diaries, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Diaries, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Dinners and Lunches, 1953-1961 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Dinners and Lunches, 1953-1961 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Dinners and Lunches - Dinner Party Lists, 1936-1945 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Dinners and Lunches - Hosts, 1950-1953 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Dinners and Lunches - Prince Akihito (Japan), 1960 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Dinners and Lunches - King Bhumibol (Thailand), 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Engagement (A-Z), 1932 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Engagement (A-Z), 1932 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - English Language Teaching, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Expense Book, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Fieldwood Farm - General, 1938-1961 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Fieldwood Farm - General, 1938-1961 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Angus Barn, 1941-1950 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Animals, 1941-1954 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Architect - Roudebush, Francis W., 1937-1942 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Construction - Costs and Estimates, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Construction - Faulkner and Kingsbury, 1935-1939 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Construction - Faulkner and Kingsbury, 1940-1942 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Construction - Todd and Brown, 1939-1941 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Fencing, 1940-1944 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Heating, 1942-1948 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Kennelly, Albert and Mae, 1944-1950 (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Landscaping and Building, 1935-1951 (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Landscaping and Building, 1935-1951 (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Perry, W. G. and Olmsted, F. L., 1937-1940 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel (CLOSED FOLDER), 1945-1955 (Box 11, Folder 98)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted material
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel - Hamilton, Harold (CLOSED FOLDER), 1948-1953 (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel - Harris, Fred (CLOSED FOLDER), 1944-1950 (Box 12, Folder 100)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel - Hunt, Coleridge (CLOSED FOLDER), 1944-1954 (Box 12, Folder 101)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel - Larsen, Robert (CLOSED FOLDER), 1940-1942 (Box 12, Folder 102)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Personnel - Welles, George W. (CLOSED FOLDER), 1940-1953 (Box 12, Folder 103)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Pool and Bathhouse, 1948-1953 (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Security, 1938-1942, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Sewage and Utilities, 1939-1950 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Specifications, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Specifications, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Tennis Court, 1947-1949 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Fieldwood Farm - Water Supply, 1948-1961 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - French Language Notes, c. 1949 (Box 13, Folder 111)
    - Guest House (New York City), 1949-1955 (Box 13, Folder 112)
    - Health Concerns, 1926-1930, 1950, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 113)
    - Hooker Electrochemical Company, 1938-1958 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - Hooker Electrochemical Company - Report, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - Indonesia Ambassadorship, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - Invitations, 1949-1961 (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - Invitations, 1949-1961 (Box 13, Folder 118)
    - Jury Duty, 1934-1964 (Box 13, Folder 119)
    - Letters of Congratulations, 1946-1957 (Box 13, Folder 120)
    - Letters of Congratulations, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 121)
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 122)
    - Naval Service, 1942-1959 (Box 14, Folder 123)
    - Naval Service, 1942-1959 (Box 14, Folder 124)
    - Naval Service - Papers, 1943-1946 (Box 14, Folder 125)
    - North Haven, 1952-1961 (Box 14, Folder 126)
    - North Haven, 1952-1961 (Box 14, Folder 127)
    - North Haven, 1952-1961 (Box 14, Folder 128)
    - North Haven - Millstream Cottage, 1955-1961 (Box 15, Folder 129)
      - North Haven - Millstream Cottage (Box P 170, Folder 1)
        Separated Materials
        Photographic material separated from the body of the collection.
    - North Haven - Witherspoon, Don, 1956-1961 (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Paintings and Works of Art, 1933-1961 (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - Paintings and Works of Art, 1933-1961 (Box 15, Folder 0131A)
    - Paintings and Works of Art, 1933-1961 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Passports, 1926-1951 (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Pocantico Hills, 1930-1961 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - Pocantico Hills, 1930-1961 (Box 15, Folder 135)
    - Pocantico Hills, 1930-1961 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    - Pocantico Hills - Alarm System, 1939-1959 (Box 15, Folder 137)
    - Pocantico Hills - Building Permits, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 138)
    - Pocantico Hills - Deed and Power of Attorney, 1938-1944, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 139)